# Vladimir Vakhter

vladimir-vakhter@outlook.com



GitHub

Worcester, MA, USA

Electrical & Computer Engineering (Ongoing Ph.D.)

vladimir-vakhter.com

Scholar

LinkedIn

# Summary

Drawing from a substantial engineering and research background, my specialization spans Electronics, Semiconductors, Software Development, Biomedical IoT Devices, Solid State Physics, and Mathematics. Over the course of 5+ years in the industry, I cultivated a wide range of technical skills and engaged in various stages of the product life cycle (concept creation, architecture, design, development, validation, and maintenance). Accumulating over a decade of research experience, I honed the abilities of critical thinking, problem analysis, and the creation of innovative solutions. I uphold a structured, meticulous, and rigorous approach to my work - consistently dedicated to elevating and sustaining high standards. I am a passionate learner. I enjoy leading and collaborating and can work both independently and jointly in fast-paced environments. I have strong communication and interpersonal abilities. Details at vladimir-vakhter.com

## Education & Coursework

CGPA: 4.0/4.0 PhD **Electrical & Computer Engineering** Worcester Polytechnic Institute, US Aug 2022 - Present MS **Electrical & Computer Engineering** Worcester Polytechnic Institute, US CGPA: 4.0/4.0 Aug 2019 - May 2021 CGPA: 5.0/5.0 Specialist (BS/MS) **Electronics & Automation** Ural Federal University, Russia Sep 2010 - Feb 2016

## **Experience**

Research Assistant @ Worcester Polytechnic Institute, US

Aug 2021 - Present

• Mixed-signal integrated circuit design, printed circuit board (PCB) design, embedded programming for biomedical IoT devices.

Signal Processing Intern @ Analog Devices, US

May 2023 - Aug 2023

Assessment and development of a physical activity (PA) monitoring algorithm bundle for a wrist-worn wearable.

Research Associate @ Worcester Polytechnic Institute, US

Jun 2021 - Jul 2022

- Developed a desktop application for communication with Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) devices. Coded in C++/Qt.
- Programmed the STM32WB55xx MCU to control peripheral units and transmit the acquired data via BLE. Coded in C with HAL.
- Designed a one-time programmable (OTP) memory to store a chip ID. Worked in Cadence Virtuoso with TSMC 180nm CMOS process.
- Built the read/write logic for the OTP memory and on-the-fly randomness test suite FIPS 140-1. Used Verilog and VHDL.
- Proposed a threat modeling methodology for resource-restricted wireless biomedical devices.

Software Engineering Intern @ Cadence Design Systems, US

May 2020 - Sep 2020

Prototyped computational geometry algorithms for design rule checking in PCBs. Coded in C++ and GLSL. Utilized OpenGL API.

**Software Engineer** @ Kalinin Machine-Building Factory, Russia

Sep 2017 - Mar 2019

- Designed real-time application and communication protocols for networked computers within a multifunctional all-terrain vehicle. Coded in C++/Qt for QNX OS. Used TCP, UDP, NTP, RPC, multithreading, mutexes, timers, and system pulses.
- Configured and maintained a GitLab server via Docker for version control.

Electrical Engineer @ Splinex (a subsidiary of IC Realtime), Russia

May 2016 - Aug 2017

- Designed component libraries, analog and digital electronic schematics, and PCBs with KiCad EDA and Altium Designer EDA.
- Developed firmware for microcontrollers. Coded in a mix of C++, Lua, and uPython.
- Prototyped, debugged, and brought up the designed hardware/PCB assemblies and low-level software.
- · Communicated with suppliers/manufacturing partners, set factory requirements. Released specifications.

### Skills

## **Software Engineering**

Programming Languages: C++ (std, Qt, SystemC), Python, Java, C, Shell, MySQL, MATLAB, Lua, uPython, Asm x51

Git (with both GitHub and GitLab), Bitbucket Version Control:

Jenkins, Bamboo, JIRA, ClickUp, Trello CI/CD, Collaboration Tools:

Google Test (C++), Junit (Java) Testina:

Troubleshooting: GDB, Valgrind, Clang

Linux (Ubuntu, Kali Linux, Fedora), Windows (incl. WSL2), QNX Neutrino Operating Systems:

**GPU Computing:** OpenGL API, GLSL, GLFW, GLAD

Virtualization Technologies: Docker, VMware Workstation Amazon Web Services - AWS (RDS, S3, API Gateway, Lambda) Cloud Technologies:

Web Development: React.js, Node.js, Bootstrap, jQuery, REST APIs, Swagger, Google Analytics, Firebase

Machine Learning: Keras

#### **Electrical & Computer Engineering**

Hardware Description Languages: Verilog/VHDL

FPGAs: Xilinx Artix A7-100T with Xilinx Vivado IDE

STM32WB55xx, STM32F3VCT6, ESP8266, Atmega2566, MSP430, ADuC847 Embedded Programming / MCUs:

Analog ASICs Design: Cadence Virtuoso, Mentor Graphics suite (Calibre, ModelSim)

Altium Designer, KiCAD EDA, Cadence Allegro Circuits / Components / PCB Design: Waveform Specification / Debugging: WaveDrom, GTKWave

Page: 1 of 2 Last Updated: August 2023

Instrumentation:	Supplies, generators, VNAs, oscilloscopes, multimeters, soldering stations, microscopes
Simulation/Modeling:	ModelSim, Mathcad, SIMetrix, Micro-Cap
Other	
Additive Manufacturing:	3D Printing (printers: Creality, Ultimaker, and LulzBot; slicers: 3DPrinterOS and Prusa; CAD: Autodesk Fusion 360) and Laser Cutting.
Natural Languages:	English (fluent) and Russian (native)

## **Publications**

#### **Journals**

- 1. [Scholar] V. Vakhter, B. Kahraman, G. Bu, F. Foroozan, and U. Guler "A Prototype Wearable Device for Noninvasive Monitoring of Transcutaneous Oxygen", IEEE TBioCAS, vol.17, no. 2, pp. 323 335, Mar. 2, 2023.
- 2. [Scholar] V. Vakhter, B. Soysal, P. Schaumont, and U. Guler, "Threat Modeling and Risk Analysis for Miniaturized Wireless Biomedical Devices", IEEE Internet of Things, vol. 9, no. 15, pp. 13338-13352, Aug.1, 2022.
- 3. [Scholar] A. Ishchenko, V. Vakhter, A. Slesarev, V. Yagodin, S. Osipov, K. Lukyashin, V. Shitov, E. Zhevak, V. Osipov, and B. Shulgin, "Thermoexoelectronic and Thermoluminescent Properties of Transparent YAG: Nd and YAG: Yb Nanoceramics", Bulletin of the Russian Academy of Sciences. Physics, vol. 78, no. 9, pp. 921 924, 2014.
- 4. V. Churmanov, S. Zyryanov, A. Ishchenko, F. Neshov, <u>V. Vakhter</u>, E. Zhevak, and D. Ilyin, "**Radiation and Thermal Methods of Synthesis of a Luminescent ZnO Coating**", Tasks of Spectroscopy and Spectrometry, vol. 30, pp. 54 58, 2012.
- 5. A. Ishchenko, B. Shulgin, O. Teslenko, L. Victorov, <u>V. Vakhter</u>, B. Slobodin, and R. Samigullina, "Luminescence and Scintillation Properties of the CsVO<sub>3</sub> Metavanadate", Tasks of Spectroscopy and Spectrometry, vol. 30, pp. 88 95, 2012.
- R. Samigullina, B. Slobodin, A. Ishchenko, B. Shulgin, L. Victorov, <u>V. Vakhter</u>, and E. Zhevak, "Radioluminescence Properties of Cs Metavanadates", News of Higher Educational Institutions: Physics, vol. 55, no. 11-3, pp. 192 193, 2012.
- 7. F. Neshov, F. Klinov, A. Ishchenko, S. Zvonarev, V. Vakhter, V. Churmanov, S. Zyryanov, and B. Shulgin, "Synthesis of Luminescent Nanostructured Coating from Zinc Oxide", Tasks of Spectroscopy and Spectrometry, vol. 29, pp. 129 133, 2011.

#### Conferences

- 1. [Scholar] A. Leonardi\*, C. Murphy\*, S. Hobson\*, V. Rohera\*, V. Vakhter\*, B. Kahraman, G. Bu, F. Foroozan, L. Rhein, and U. Guler, "Optimizing Transcutaneous Oxygen Measurement Sites on Humans", 2023 IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Conference (EMBC), Jul. 24 27, 2023, Sydney, Australia, pp.1–4 (\*equal contribution).
- 2. [Scholar] B. Kahraman\*, V. Vakhter\*, I. Costanzo, G. Bu, F. Foroozan, and U. Guler, "A Miniaturized Prototype for Continuous Noninvasive Transcutaneous Oxygen Monitoring", 2022 IEEE Biomedical Circuits and Systems Conference (BioCAS), Oct. 13-15, 2022, Taipei, Taiwan, pp.486 490 (\* equal contribution).
- 3. [Scholar] V. Vakhter, B. Soysal, P. Schaumont, and U. Guler, "Minimum On-the-node Data Security for the Next-generation Miniaturized Wireless Biomedical Devices", 63<sup>rd</sup> International Midwest Symposium on Circuits and Systems, MWSCAS'20, Aug. 2020, pp. 1068 1071.
- 4. <u>V. Vakhter</u> and A. Druzhinin, "Multifunctional Magneto-Optical System for Measuring Magnetic Characteristics of Ferromagnets", 2<sup>nd</sup> International Youth Conference, Physics. Technologies. Innovations. PTI 2015, April 2015. pp. 87 88.
- 5. <u>V. Vakhter</u> and A. Druzhinin, "Measurement of the magnetic characteristics of ferromagnetics by a magneto-optical method", 21st All-Russian Scientific Conference of Young Physicists and Scientists, VNKSF-21, March April 2015. pp. 258 259.
- V. Vakhter and A. Druzhinin, "Multifunctional Optical Device for Measuring Magnetic Characteristics of Ferromagnets", 20th All-Russian Scientific Conference of Young Physicists and Scientists, VNKSF-20, March – April 2014. pp. 248 – 249.
- 7. V. Yagodin, E. Zhevak, <u>V. Vakhter</u>, M. Zuev , A. Vasin, A. Ishchenko, and B. Shulgin, "Radioluminescence Properties of Eu Doped Strontium Gadolinium Oxyapatites", 10<sup>th</sup> Issyk-Kul Conference on Radiation Physics, SCORPh 2013, July–August 2013, pp. 17–19.
- 8. <u>V. Vakhter</u>, E. Zhevak, A. Yarkov, A. Ishchenko, L. Victorov, and B. Shulgin, "Composite Organic-and-Inorganic Scintillators Based on Polycrystalline Fluorides", 10<sup>th</sup> Issyk-Kul Conference on Radiation Physics, SCORPh 2013, July August 2013. pp. 94 95.
- V. Vakhter, A. Ishchenko, A.Slesarev, and S. Osipov, "Thermoexoelectronic Emission and Thermally Stimulated Luminescence of the Transparent YAG:Nd<sup>3+</sup> and YAG:Yb<sup>3+</sup> Nanoceramics", 14<sup>th</sup> All-Russian School-Seminar on the Problems of the Condensed Matter Physics, SPFKS-14, November 2013. p. 250.
- 10. R. Samigullina, B. Slobodin, A. Ishchenko, B. Shulgin, L. Victorov, <u>V. Vakhter</u>, and E. Zhevak, "Radioluminescence Properties of Cs Metavanadates", 3<sup>rd</sup> International Congress on Radiation Physics and Chemistry of Condensed Matter, High Current Electronics and Modification of Materials with Particle Beams and Plasma Flows, September 2012. pp. 132 133.
- 11. A. Ishchenko, <u>V. Vakhter</u>, E. Zhevak, V. Churmanov, and S. Zyryanov, "Nano Zinc Oxide Scintillation Coating", International Scientific Youth Symposium "Biosphere's safety 2012", May 2012. pp. 71 72.

Page: 2 of 2 Last Updated: August 2023